Charity Cannon Willard Papers, 1891-2006
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Charity Cannon Willard papers
Willard, Charity Cannon
MS 558
4 boxes (4 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Papers of Charity Cannon Willard, biographer of early French feminist and author Christine de Pizan (1363-1440). Included are writings by Charity Cannon Willard and others about Christine de Pizan and microfilmed manuscripts and other source materials collected by Willard.
Charity Cannon Willard was born in Eureka, Illinois, August 9, 1914. She earned her A.B. at Hiram College in 1934, her M.A. in French at Smith College in 1936, and her Ph.D. in Romance Philology at Radcliffe College/Harvard University in 1940. She studied at the Radcliffe Institute for Independent Study from 1962 to 1966, and at the Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes in Paris during the 1967-1968 academic year. She was married to Sumner Willard, a colonel at West Point Military Academy. Since West Point officers' wives were not permitted to work fulltime outside the home, Willard declined the offer of a professorship at Brown University and instead taught children at West Point and spent time in Europe searching for existing manuscripts of Christine de Pizan. She later taught at Ladycliff College, a women's college in Highland Falls, N.Y. (now closed). She was the first West Point colonel's wife to pursue a professional career. Willard became an internationally recognized authority on France's first professional woman of letters, Christine de Pizan, and is credited with establishing de Pizan's reputation in the English-speaking world. She was the author of Christine de Pizan: Her Life and Works (New York: Persea Books, 1984), and produced many translations and critical editions of de Pizan's work.
Willard was awarded the Ordres des Palmes Academiques by the French government in 1984, the Distinguished Alumnae Award from Hiram College in 1988, an L.H.D. from Saint Mary College in 1993, and a Smith College Medal in 1998. She died June 5, 2005.
Christine de Pizan (1363-1440) was the daughter of Tommaso di Benvenuto da Pizzano, a lecturer in astrology at the University of Bologna (1348) and later a physician. Shortly after Christine's birth, her father became court astrologer to Charles V, moving the family to Paris in 1368. De Pizan was educated by her father in spite of her mother's objections, and was married at age fifteen to Étienne du Castel, a royal secretary, who encouraged her to continue her studies. She was widowed at age twenty-five and left with three children, a niece, and her own widowed mother to support; her father had died impoverished, and her husband's estate took fourteen years and numerous lawsuits to close. Most feminist scholars date the beginning of the modern feminist movement to the works of Christine de Pizan. She was France's, and possibly Europe's, first woman known to have earned her living by the pen; she is also considered by some scholars to be Europe's first professional writer, male or female. While establishing her reputation as a writer, she earned her living by copying and illustrating other people's works. Her works included all genres: biography, autobiography, poetry, history, novels, short stories, feminist polemics, books on advice and morality, military techniques, religion, politics, and literary commentary.
[See also APPENDIX: PUBLICATIONS ON CHRISTINE DE PIZAN]
The collection contains writings by Charity Cannon Willard and others about Christine de Pizan (1363-1440), including essays, lectures, articles, notes, and books. There are approximately 40 reels of microfilm of source materials collected by Willard as well as slides and photographs of original manuscripts from other archival repositories.
This collection is organized into seven series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. NOTES
III. WRITINGS
IV. LECTURES AND CONFERENCE PAPERS
V. SUBJECT FILES: CHRISTINE DE PIZAN
VI. AUDIOVISUAL
VII. OVERSIZED MATERIALS
BOOKS
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
History of the Collection
The Charity Cannon Willard Papers were donated by her estate in 2006.
Search Terms
Feminism--France--History--Sources; Feminists--France--Biography--Sources; Authors, French--To 1500--Biography; French literature--To 1500; Christine, de Pisan, ca. 1364-ca. 1431--Biography--Sources; Willard, Charity Cannon; Christine, de Pisan, ca. 1364-ca. 1431; The writings of Christine de Pizan. Ed. Charity Cannon Willard--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Associated material located in Smith College Archives, Smith Medalists files.
APPENDIX: Publications on Christine de Pizan
Books
Édition Critique of Le Livre de la paix, by Christine de Pizan. The Hague: Mouton, 1958.
Christine de Pizan, Her Life and Works. New York: Persea, 1985.
Text established in collaboration with Eric Hicks. Le Livre des trois vertus. Paris: Champion, 1989.
Translator of A Medieval Woman's Mirror of Honor: The Treasury of the City of Ladies. ed. Madeleine Pelner Cosman. New York: Persea, 1989.
Editor of The Writings of Christine de Pizan. New York: Persea, 1993.
Editor of The Book of Arms and of Chivalry, by Christine de Pizan. Trans. B. G. Sumner Willard. University Park, Penn.: Pennsylvania State University Press, 1999.
Foreword to Christine de Pizan: A Casebook. New York, NY: Routledge; 2003. xiii, pp. 296
The "Livre de la Paix" of Christine de Pizan: A Critical Edition with Introduction and Notes. The Hague: Mouton, 1958.
Editor. Les Faits d'armes et de chevalerie. Édition critique. Forthcoming.
Book Reviews
Review of: Rains, R.R., ed. Les Sept Psaumes allégorisés. in Romance Philology. Vol. XXI, No. 1. Berkeley: University of California Press, August 1967.
Review of: Hicks, Eric. "Le Débat sur le Roman de la Rose." 1977.
Review of: McLeod, Enid. The Order of the Rose: The Life and Ideas of Christine de Pizan.
Book Articles
"Isabel of Portugal, Patroness of Humanism?" in Simone, Franco. Miscellanea di studi e recherché sul Quatrocento francese. Torino: Gioppichelli, 1967. 519-544.
"Christine de Pizan on the Art of Warfare" in Desmond, Marilynn, ed. Christine de Pizan and the Categories of Difference. Minneapolis, MN: U of Minnesota P; 1998. pp. 3-15. xix, 287 pp. in Essays in Honor of L. F. Solano, ed. Raymond Cormier and Urban Holmes. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1970.
"A Fifteenth-Century View of Women's Role in Medieval Society: Christine de Pizan's Livre des Trois Vertus" In Morewedge, Rosemarie Thee. The Role of Women in the Middle Ages, Papers of the sixth annual conference of the Center for Medieval and Early Renaissance Study, State University of New York at Binghamton 6-7 May 1972. Albany and London: State University of New York Press and Hodder and Stroughton, 1975. 90-120.
"Christine de Pizan, The Astrologer's Daughter." in Moyen Age et Renaissance, ed. Jonathan Beck and Gianni Mombello. Vol. 1 of Mélanges à la mémoire de Franco Simone: France et Italie dans la culture européenne. Geneva: Slatkine, 1980.
"A New Look at Christine de Pizan's Epistre au dieu d'Amours" In Beck, Jonathan and Mombello, Gianni. Seconda miscellanea di studi e ricerche sul quatttrocento francese. Chambéry et Turin, Centre d'études franco-italien. 1981. 71-92.
"Christine de Pizan and the Order of the Rose" in Ideals for Women in the Works of Christine de Pizan, ed. Diane Bornstein. Michigan Consortium of Medieval and Early Modern Studies Monograph Series 1. 1981.
"Christine de Pizan's 'Cent ballades d'amant et de dame': Criticism of Courtly Love" in Burgess, Glyn S. (ed.); Deyermond, A. D. (ed.); Jackson, W. H. (ed.); Mills, A. D. (ed.); Ricketts, P. T. (ed.); Court and Poet: Selected Proceedings of the Third Congress of the International Courtly Literature Society, Liverpool, 1980. Liverpool: Cairns; 1981. pp. 357-364. xii, 364 pp.
"Christine de Pizan's Livre des Trois Vertus: Feminine Ideal or Practical Advice?" in Ideals for Women in the Works of Christine de Pizan, ed. Diane Bornstein. Michigan Consortium of Medieval and Early Modern Studies Monograph Series 1. 1981.
"The Duke of Berry's Multiple Copies of the Fleur des histoires d'Orient" in Bichakjian, Bernard H. (ed.); From Linguistics to Literature: Romance Studies Offered to Francis M. Rogers. Amsterdam: Benjamins; 1981. pp. 281-292. 292 pp.
"The Franco-Italian Professional Writer: Christine de Pizan" in Janssens, G. A. M. (ed.); Aarts, F. G. A. M. (ed.); Studies in Seventeenth-Century English Literature, History, and Bibliography: Festschrift for Professor T. A. Birrell on the Occasion of His Sixtieth Birthday. Amsterdam: Rodopi; 1984. pp. 333-363 vii, 268 pp.
"Concepts of Love according to Guillaume de Machaut, Christine de Pizan, and Pietro Bembo" in Burgess, Glyn S. (ed.); Taylor, Robert A. (ed.); Deyermond, Alan (ed.); Green, Dennis (ed.); Rowland, Beryl (ed.); The Spirit of the Court: Selected Proceedings of the Fourth Congress of the International Courtly Literature Society (Toronto 1983). Dover, NH: Brewer; 1985. pp. 386-392, 408 pp.
"Margaret of Austria: Regent of the Netherlands" in Wilson, Katharina M. (ed.); Women Writers of the Renaissance and Reformation. Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1987. pp. 350-362
"Punishment and Reward in Christine de Pizan's Lyric Poetry" In Davies, Peter V., and Kennedy, Angus J. Rewards and Punishment in the Arthurian Romances and Lyric Poetry of Medieval France, Essays Presented to Kenneth Varty on the Occasion of His Sixtieth Birthday. Cambridge: D.S. Brewer (Arthurian studies, XVII), 1987. 165-174.
"Christine de Pizan on Chivalry" in Chickering, Howell (ed. and introd.); Seiler, Thomas H. (ed.); The Study of Chivalry: Resources and Approaches. Kalamazoo, MI: Medieval Institute, Western Michigan University, 1988. 511-28.
"Raoul de Presles's Translation of Saint Augustine's De Civitate Dei" in Beer, Jeanette (ed.); Medieval Translators and Their Craft. Kalamazoo: Medieval Institute, Western Michigan University, 1989. pp. 329-346.
"Jean de Werchin, Seneschal de Hainaut: Reader and Writer of Courtly Literature" in Busby, Keith (ed.); Kooper, Erik (ed.); Courtly Literature: Culture and Context. Amsterdam: Benjamins; 1990. pp. 595-603.
"L'idée du Bonheur chez Christine de Pizan" In Bushinger, Danielle. L'Idée du bonheur au moyen âge, Actes du Colloque d'Amiens de mars 1984. Göppingen, Kümmerle (Göppinger Arbeiten zur Germanistik, CDXIX), 1990. 97-102.
"Anne de France, Reader of Christine de Pizan" in McLeod, Glenda K. Visitors to the City: Readers of Christine Pizan. Lewiston, NY: Edward Mellen, 1991.
"Antoine de la Salle, Reader of Christine de Pizan" in McLeod, Glenda K. Visitors to the City: Readers of Christine Pizan. Lewiston, NY: Edward Mellen, 1991.
"Christine de Pizan" in Sartori, Eva Martin (ed.); Zimmerman, Dorothy Wynne; French Women Writers: A Bio-Bibliographical Source Book. New York: Greenwood; 1991. pp. 56-65.
"Christine de Pizan." in Vol. 2 of An Encyclopedia of Continental Women Writers, ed. Katherina M. Wilson. New York and London: Garland, 1991.
"Christine de Pizan: From Poet to Political Commentator" in Brabant, Margaret (ed.); Elshtain, Jean Bethke (introd.); Politics, Gender, and Genre: The Political Thought of Christine de Pizan. Boulder: Westview; 1992. pp. 17-32. xii, 240 pp.
"Une Source oubliée du voyage imaginaire de Christine de Pizan" in Aubailly, Jean-Claude, Baumgartner; Emmanuèle; Dubost, Francis; Dulac, Liliane; and Faure, Marcel. "Et c'est la fin pour que sommes ensemble," hommage à Jean Dufournet: littérature, histoire, et langue du moyen âge. Paris: Champion, t. I, 1993. 321-326.
"Christine de Pizan's Allegorized Psalms" in Dulac, Liliane and Ribémont, Bernard. Une femme de Lettres au moyen âge: études réunies autour de Christine de Pizan. Orléans: Paradigme, 1995. 317-324
. "Pilfering Vegetius? Christine de Pizan's 'Faits d'Armes et de Chevalerie' " in Smith, Lesley (ed.); Taylor, Jane H. M. (ed.); Women, the Book and the Worldly. Cambridge: D. S. Brewer; 1995. pp. 31-37.
"Gilles de Chin in History, Literature, and Folklore" in Kelly, Douglas (ed.); The Medieval Opus: Imitation, Rewriting, and Transmission in the French Tradition. Amsterdam: Rodopi; 1996. 357-66.
"The Patronage of Isabel of Portugal" in McCash, June Hall (ed.); Nichols, Stephen G. (foreword); The Cultural Patronage of Medieval Women. Athens, GA: University of Georgia Press, 1996. 306-20.
"Louis de Bruges, lecteur de Christine de Pizan" In Cahiers de Recherches Médiévales. XIII-XV s. 4, 1997. pp. 191-195.
"The Dominican Abbey of Poissy in 1400" in Campbell, John (ed. and preface); Margolis, Nadia (ed. and introd.); Christine de Pizan 2000. Amsterdam, Netherlands: Rodopi; 2000. pp. 209-18. 429 pp.
"A Singular Career: College Professor and Army Wife" (1914- ) In Chance, Jane (ed. and introd.); Women Medievalists and the Academy. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 2005. 759-68.
Journal Articles
"The 'Three Virtues' of Christine de Pizan." In Boston Public Library Quarterly (1950): 201-305.
"Christine de Pizan's 'Clock of Temperance.'" L'Esprit Créateur 2 (1962): 149-54.
"A Portuguese Translation of Christine de Pisan's Livre des Trois Vertus" PMLA: Publications of the Modern Language Association of America 78 (1963): 459-64.
"An Autograph Manuscript of Christine de Pizan." Studi Francesi 78 (1965): 452-57.
"Isabel of Portugal and the French Translation of the Triunfo de las donas" Revue Belge de Philologie et d'Histoire/Belgische Tijdschrift voor Filologieen Geschiedenis, 1965; 43: 961-969.
"The Manuscript Tradition of Le Livre des Trois Vertus and Christine de Pizan's Audience." Journal of the History of Ideas 27 (1966): 433-44.
"The Remarkable Case of Clotilde de Surville" L'Esprit Créateur, 1966; 6: 108-116.
"The Concept of True Nobility at the Burgundian Court" Studies in the Renaissance, 1967; 14: 33-48.
"A Fifteenth-Century Burgundian Version of the Roman de Florimont"Medievalia et Humanistica. II (n.s.). 1971. 21-46.
"A Re-Examination of Le Débat des deux amants"Les Bonnes Feuilles. III. 1974. 73-88.
"An Unknown Manuscript of Christine de Pizan's Livre de la paix" Studi Francesi, 1978; 64: 90-97.
"Jean Bodel and Christine de Pizan, Pastoral Poets" Marche Romane, 1980; 30 (3-4): 293-300.
"Lovers' Dialogues in Christine de Pizan's Lyric Poetry from the Cent ballades to the Cent ballades d'Amant et de Dame" Fifteenth-Century Studies, 1981; 4: 167-180.
"Essor et Fortune de la Chanson de Geste dans l'Europe et l'orient latin" Actes du IXe Congrès International de la Société Rencesvals pour l'Étude des Épopées Romanes. Padoue-Venise: Mucchi Editore, 29 Aug. - 4 Sept., 1982.
"Florent et Octavien: The Fourteenth-Century Poem" Olifant: A Publication of the Société Rencesvals, American-Canadian Branch, 1989 Fall-Winter; 14 (3-4): 179-189.
"Women and Marriage Around 1400: Three Views" Fifteenth-Century Studies, 1990; 17: 475-484.
"Christine de Pizan as Teacher" Romance Languages Annual, 1992; 3: 132-36.
"L'influence de l'image sur l'imagination de Christine de Pizan"Wodam, 1992.
"Renard et ses compagnons dans les sermons de Jean Gerson" Reinardus: Yearbook of the International Reynard Society/Annuaire de la Société Internationale Renardienne, 1992; 5: 209-15.
Replies to the Following Articles
"Dignity and Desire: The Alba Poet's Liberation of the Courtly Lady" By: Sigal, Gale; in O'Nan, Martha (ed.); Papers on Romance Literary Relations: The Creation of Female Voices by Male Writers in Romance Literatures. Brockport: State University of New York; 1987. pp. 9-20.
"Doing unto Others as Was Done unto Her: The pícara in Spanish Golden Age Fiction" By: Ackerlind, Sheila R. in O'Nan, Martha (ed.); Papers on Romance Literary Relations: The Creation of Female Voices by Male Writers in Romance Literatures. Brockport: State Univ. of New York; 1987. pp. 23-29.
"Enide and Fenice: Chrétien de Troyes's Clerkly Heroines" By: Armstrong, Grace M. In O'Nan, Martha (ed.); Papers on Romance Literary Relations: The Creation of Female Voices by Male Writers in Romance Literatures. Brockport: State Univ.of New York; 1987. pp. 1-8.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Personal photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cornwall-on-the-Hudson Reading Club records (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trip to Poissy (Postcards, tour guide) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Smith College medal (which incorrectly states that CCW was a member of the undergraduate class of '36) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Letters, postcards, etc. (detailed list within folder) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: List of colleagues' addresses (Box 1, Folder 6)
- SERIES II. NOTES
  - J. Germain "Débat du Chrétien et du Sarrazin" (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Morea-Rendu "Poissy" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Dictionnaire des littératures de langue française" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Le Champion des dames" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Un Poème inédit" (with copy of text) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Livre des faits d'armes" (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "L'Épître d'Othéa" (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "La Chronique de Bergues" (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Obras de Rodriguez de la Cámera (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous topics (Box 1, Folder 16)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS, [See also SERIES VII. OVERSIZED MATERIALS]]
  - Unpublished
    - "Jeanne d'Arc comme Source d'Inspiration R: Héraire au quinzième siècle" M.A. Thesis, Smith College, 1936. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "The Miracles of Notre Dame," 1937. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Looking Eastward Around 1400," paper proposal. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Published
    - Review of: Rains, R.R., ed. Les Sept Psaumes allégorisés. 1967. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Review of: Hicks, Eric. "Le Débat sur le Roman de la Rose." 1977. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "L'influence de l'image sur l'imagination de Christine de Pizan," with offprint, 1992. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Louis de Bruges, Lecteur de Christine de Pizan," with offprints (3), 1997. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "The Dominican Abbey of Poissy in 1400," with offprints (2), notes, and copy of Christine de Pizan's "Le Dit de Poissy," 2000. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "Women and Marriage Around 1400: Three Views" (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Margaret of Austria" (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - " Jean Bodel and Christine de Pizan, Pastoral Poets," with offprint (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Chapter 1: Antoine de Salle, Reader of Christine de Pizan" and "Chapter 5: Anne de France, Reader of Christine de Pizan" (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "On Isabel of Portugal and the Court of Burgundy" (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Christine de Pizan's Allegorized Psalms," in French and English, with English offprints (3) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - "Christine de Pizan as Teacher" (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Review of: McLeod, Enid. The Order of the Rose: The Life and Ideas of Christine de Pizan. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous Works
    - "Amazons in Christine de Pizan's City of Ladies" (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "A Backward Glance" (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "Christine de Pizan's Attack on Courtly Love" (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Christine de Pizan, Biographer of Charles V" (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "Christine de Pizan's Concept of the Just War" (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "Christine de Pizan's Debt to Boccaccio" (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "The Flemish Cité des Dames" (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - "Medieval Women: The Court as a School for Young Noblewomen" (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - "Proverbs in the Writing of Christine de Pizan" (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - "Text and Image in the Manuscripts of Christine de Pizan's Works" (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Offprints of published works
    - "A Portuguese Translation of Christine de Pizan's Livre des Trois Vertus," 1963, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - "The Manuscript Tradition of the Livre des Trois Vertus and Christine de Pizan's Audience," 1966, 2 copies (Box 1)
    - "Christine de Pizan's Treatise on the Art of Warfare," 1970, 2 copies (Box 1)
    - "Lovers' Dialogues in Christine de Pizan's Lyric Poetry from the Cent Ballades to the Cent Ballades d'Amant et de Dame," 1981 (Box 1)
    - "L'idée de bonheur au moyen âge," 1990 (Box 1)
    - "Pilfering Vegetius? Christine de Pizan's Faits d'Armes et de Chevalerie," 1995 (Box 1)
    - "Concepts of Love According to Guillaume de Machaut, Christine de Pizan and Pietro Bembo" (Box 1)
    - "Une Source Oubliée du Voyage Imaginaire de Christine de Pizan," 3 copies (Box 1)
    - "Punishment and Reward in Christine de Pizan's Lyric Poetry," 2 copies (Box 1)
    - "Essor et fortune de la chanson de geste dans l'Europe et l'Orient Latin,"offprint only, 1982. (Box 1)
  - Reviews of published works
    - "Christine de Pizan, Her Life and Works", [See also SERIES VII. OVERSIZED MATERIALS]] (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Ferrante, Joan M. "Medieval Woman and Poet: Christine de Pizan, Her Life and Works" (Box 1)
    - "Christine de Pizan" Book World, February 10, 1985. (Box 1)
    - "Guardian Women" (Box 1)
- SERIES IV. LECTURES AND CONFERENCE PAPERS
  - Scholarly
    - "Christine de Pizan and the Seneschal of Hainault," Kalamazoo: 1978 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - "Christine de Pizan's Imaginary Voyage to the East," Europe and Asia: 600-1600 Institution and Ideas Conference, University of Hawaii at Manoa: January 2-5, 1983 (accompanying drafts, notes, program, and manuscript photographs) (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - "Recreating a Medieval Person," Tulane University: February 17, 1989 (accompanying confirmation letter, multiple drafts, and French version of the essay) (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - "Christine de Pizan: From Poet to Political Commentator," The Political Theory of Christine de Pizan, University of Virginia: October 20, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - "Christine de Pizan, Reader of Arthurian Romance," XVIth International Arthurian Conference, Durham: August 11-18, 1990 (accompanying program and list of participants) (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - "Christine de Pizan as Teacher," Purdue University Conference on Romance Languages, Literatures & Film, West Lafayette, IN: October 3-5, 1991(multiple copies) (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - "Bruges: The 'Venice of the North'," 1992 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - "Pilfering Vegetius? Christine de Pizan's Faits d'Armes et de Chevalerie," Woman and the Book in the Middle Ages, St. Hilda's College, Oxford: August 27-30, 1993 (accompanying manuscript photographs and program) (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - "Not Always a Feminist: Christine de Pizan on the Art of Warfare," Christine de Pizan: Texts/Intertexts/Contexts, Binghamton, NY: October 20-21, 1995 (accompanying program and invitation letter) (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - "Christine de Pizan on War and Peace" (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - "Christine de Pizan in Print," Cleveland (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - "Early Readers of Christine de Pizan: Some Medieval Women to Be Remembered," La Maison Française, New York University: February 13 (multiple copies) (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - "Late Medieval Mysticism" (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - "Lovers' Dialogues in Christine de Pizan's Lyric Poetry from The 'Cent to the 'Cent Ballades d'Amant et de Dame' " (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - "Michel de Montaigne" (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - "St. Bernard and a Duchess of Burgundy," Cleveland State University (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Popular
    - "The Cadfael Chronicles of Ellis Peters" (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - "A Peace to End All Peace" (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - "The Russian Ballet" (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - "The Court of Tamerlan" (accompanying news clipping and photocopied text) (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - "Leningrad" (accompanying notes and article) (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - "The End of the Spanish Empire" (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - "Americans in Paris: The Lost Generation" (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - "Is the World Flat?" (accompanying comic strip) (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - "Tristan and Iseut" (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - "Jean-Paul Sartre" (Box 1, Folder 70)